const e=JSON.parse('[{"question":"On administration of an unknown dose of a new antipsychotic, a 55-year- old man develops extra pyramidal symptoms. The dose at which this effect appears would be established in which phase of clinical trials?","options":{"A":"Phase 1","B":"Phase 2","C":"Preclinical phase","D":"Phase 3","E":"Phase 4"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The dose at which side-effects develop is often determined at phase 1 of clinical trials. The pathway that a drug must follow before approval and marketing starts with animal studies, where the molecule is demonstrated to have specifi c actions. These extensive, preclinical animal studies must be carried out on at least two different animal species. Mutagenicity, carcinogenicity, and organ system toxicity are studies at this phase. A new drug under investigation then enters human trials. The fi rst phase consists of determining if the drug is safe on human subjects. It is administered to a small group of volunteers and safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of the drug are ascertained. In phase 2, effectiveness in comparison to placebo is studied in hundreds of patients with the target disease to see if it works at all against the disease. In phase 3, the drug undergoes extensive double- blind, randomized controlled trials to determine how well it works and what are the common side- effects. Phase 4 takes place if all the previous phases are successfully crossed—the drug undergoes the approval process by regulatory bodies and postmarketing surveillance ensues. Less common side-effects, which sometimes could lead to a drug’s withdrawal, can be picked up when large-scale prescribing takes place during postmarketing surveillance. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004. p. 2708."},{"question":"Haloperidol is more potent than chlorpromazine. Potency of a therapeutic formulation refers to","options":{"A":"Strength of binding to receptors","B":"Duration of action at receptors","C":"Size of the dose required to produce an effect","D":"Elimination half-life of a drug","E":"Proportion of available receptors occupied by a drug"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Potency of a drug with receptor-binding action refers to the amount of the drug needed to produce a particular effect compared to another standard drug with similar receptor profi le (‘vigour’). Affi nity refers to the ability of the drug to bind to its appropriate receptor (‘affection’). Effi cacy refers to how well the drug produces the expected response, that is the maximum clinical response produced by a drug (‘productivity’). Effi cacy depends on affi nity, potency, duration of receptor action in some cases, and kinetic properties such as half-life, among other factors. Haloperidol is more potent than chlorpromazine as approximately 5 mg of haloperidol is required to achieve the same effect as 100 mg of chlorpromazine. These drugs, however, are equal in the maximal clinical response achievable using them, that is equally effi cacious but not equipotent. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 985."},{"question":"Absorption of orally administered drugs is affected by which of the following","options":{"A":"Intestinal transit","B":"Co-administered drugs","C":"P-glycoprotein","D":"Presence of food","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"After oral administration, a drug may be incompletely absorbed. This is mainly due to lack of absorption from the intestine related to the presence of inhibitory factors such as food or gastric acid, or to changes in intestinal motility; for example having diarrhoea or vomiting can affect drug absorption. Inherent properties of certain drugs can also affect their absorption, for example highly hydrophilic drugs cannot cross the lipid cell membrane, while highly lipophilic drugs will struggle to cross the water layer in extracellular space. Presence of reverse transporters, such as P-glycoprotein, can affect drug absorption. P-glycoprotein pumps certain drug molecules actively out into the gut lumen from gut cells. Inhibition of P-glycoprotein and gut wall metabolism, for example by grapefruit juice, can increase absorption of certain (mostly non-psychotropic) medications. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 2700.138 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following conditions predisposes to a higher rate of transport through the blood–brain barrier?","options":{"A":"Presence of ionized drug molecules","B":"Presence of protein-bound drug molecules","C":"Presence of water-soluble drug molecules","D":"Presence of inflamed meninges","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The blood–brain barrier poses a special challenge to the transit of drug molecules into the brain, which is very important to ensure the activity of most psychotropics. The blood–brain barrier is a structural and functional barrier comprised of capillary endothelium of brain, which possesses tight junctions, acting in unison as a single sheet or membrane. These junctions are disrupted when meningitis or other infl ammation affects the structure. The ability of a drug to pass the blood–brain barrier depends on its molecular size, lipid solubility, and ionic status. Unionized molecules that are freely available and less protein bound are transported across the barrier easily. In general, the higher the lipid water partition coeffi cient, the greater the ability to cross the barrier. Exceptionally, there are a few molecules that pass the barrier effectively in spite of having a low lipid–water partition coeffi cient. These have specifi c carrier mechanisms, for example amino acid transport system (this is stereo specifi c, so that L amino acids but not D amino acids are easily transferred). L-dopa and valproate have specifi c carrier mechanisms. Some areas of brain lack this barrier—subfornical organ, area postrema, and median eminence. These circumventricular organs allow transfer of many compounds from blood to brain. This may have a survival benefi t as certain toxic substances stimulate the area postrema and induce nausea and vomiting. Johnstone E et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 38."},{"question":"A 72-year-old patient with bipolar illness experiences more side-effects when taking the same medication that he was prescribed 30 years ago, when he was 42 years old. Which of the following is a possible explanation?","options":{"A":"Reduced proportion of body fat","B":"Increased liver enzyme activity","C":"Increased renal clearance of drugs","D":"Increased protein-binding fraction","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Pharmacokinetic changes in old age are pertinent when considering initiation, dosing, and coadministration of medications in the elderly. In general, the ability to absorb an orally administered medication is not greatly affected, but elderly patients have less body fat, and so lipid-soluble drugs may be distributed to brain tissue more avidly. However, this effect is not universal for all drugs. Protein binding and hepatic metabolism are reduced in elderly people, especially when malnourished. Renal function invariably drops with age. Note that this question is non-specifi c with respect to the prescribed drug. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1278."},{"question":"Which one of the following has partial agonistic activity as a major therapeutic mechanism?","options":{"A":"Propranalol","B":"Olanzapine","C":"Lithium","D":"Pindolol","E":"Carbamazepine"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Pindolol is a partial agonist at β-receptor sites. In addition, it is a 5-HT antagonist 1A and has been studied as an augmenting agent with antidepressants. The fi nal common pathway of action of most psychotropics is interference with neurotransmitter function. In general, neurotransmitters are released from a presynaptic neurone, occupy a receptor in a postsynaptic neurone, and bring about a change in the activity of the postsynaptic neurone. If a drug acts in a similar fashion to a neurotransmitter and brings about a similar change in the postsynaptic neurone, then it is called an agonist. This is often due to the intrinsic activity of the drug molecule on the specifi c receptors. Certain drugs occupy the receptors and do not have any intrinsic activity; they simply stop the neurotransmitter from carrying out its routine function. These drugs are called antagonists for the particular receptor. Certain other drugs have a degree of intrinsic activity; thus, when there is no indigenous neurotransmitter in the vicinity, they can produce a degree of effect similar to the neurotransmitter but if these molecules are allowed to compete with the indigenous neurotransmitters, this becomes counter productive. They block the full action that could be provided by the neurotransmitter. Hence, these are called partial agonists. Propranalol is a β-agonist with both β1- and β2-antagonistic properties. Olanzapine is predominantly a serotonin (5-HT ) and dopamine antagonist (D2). Carbamazepine is a 2A membrane-stabilizing agent while the mechanism of action of lithium is thought to be mediated via the second messenger inositol system. The anxiolytic buspirone is a partial agonist at 5-HT 1A autoreceptors. Aripiprazole is also a partial agonist at dopamine receptors. Oliver JS, Cryan JF, Burrows GD et al. Pindolol augmentation of antidepressants: a review and rationale. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry 2000; 34: 71–79.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 139"},{"question":"A 44-year-old in-patient, recently started on clozapine, develops exacerbation of chronic sinusitis and appears excessively drowsy. All of the following remedial measures might interfere with clozapine metabolism except","options":{"A":"Coffee","B":"Quitting smoking","C":"Amoxicillin","D":"Erythromycin","E":"Ciprofl oxacin"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Amoxicillin is largely cleared through the kidneys and does not interfere with clozapine metabolism. Clozapine undergoes hepatic metabolism via CYP1A2, CYP3A4, and CYP2D6. Ciprofl oxacin and other fl uoroquinolone antibiotics can inhibit CYP1A2 and affect clozapine levels. Smoking induces CYP1A2 and quitting it will lead to a rebound inhibition effect on the enzyme appearing after 2 to 4 weeks. Byproducts of tobacco smoking, particularly the polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, are the major offenders in this regard. The metabolic inductive effects are not specifi c to tobacco smoking as they can also be expected from marijuana smoking. Erythromycin inhibits CYP3A4; this may lead to increase in clozapine levels. Caffeine has the opposite effect of smoking on clozapine metabolism. It inhibits CYP1A2 enzyme, leading to higher clozapine levels. Worrel JA, Marken PA, Beckman SE et al. Atypical antipsychotic agents: A critical review. American Journal of Health-System Pharmacy 2000; 57: 238–255."},{"question":"Imipramine is a tricyclic antidepressant. Which one of the following is true with respect to imipramine?","options":{"A":"It acts synergistically with ECT.","B":"Imipramine has no effect in atypical depression.","C":"Imipramine and CBT are equally effective in severe depression.","D":"Imipramine decreases non-REM sleep.","E":"Imipramine is not toxic in overdose."},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Imipramine seems to be synergistic with ECT; it is shown to be more effective than SSRIs in preventing relapse following ECT in depressed patients (Lauritzen et al., 1996). Monoamine oxidase inhibitors have been shown to be more effective than tricyclics in atypical depressive disorders with biological features such as increased sleep and increased appetite. Though imipramine may not be as effective as MAOIs, it has been shown to be better than placebo in atypical depression. An often-quoted study that undertook head-to-head comparison of CBT and imipramine is the National Institute of Mental Health Depression Study (Elkin et al., 1989). In this study 16 weeks of CBT, imipramine, interpersonal therapy (IPT), and placebo were compared. Among the less-severely depressed patients, comparable proportions achieved remission in all three active treatment arms; but among the more-depressed patients, imipramine was superior to CBT in terms of remission rates achieved. Imipramine alters sleep structure considerably; it reduces REM (rapid eye movement) sleep and increases NREM (non-REM) sleep. All tricyclics are toxic in overdose; tertiary amines such as amitriptyline and imipramine produce longer-acting metabolites and have higher toxic potential than secondary amines. Elkin I, Shea T, Watkins JT et al. National Institute of Mental Health treatment of depression collaborative research program. Archives of General Psychiatry 1989; 46: 971–982. Lauritzen L, Odgaard K, Clemmesen L et al. Relapse prevention by means of paroxetine in ECT- treated patients with major depression: a comparison with imipramine and placebo in medium- term continuation therapy. Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica 1996; 94: 241–251. McGrath PJ, Stewart JW, Janal MN et al. A placebo-controlled study of fl uoxetine versus imipramine in the acute treatment of atypical depression. American Journal of Psychiatry 2000; 157: 344–350."},{"question":"Use of stimulants is relatively contraindicated in which of the following patients with ADHD?","options":{"A":"9-year-old child with a family history of ADHD","B":"9-year-old child with a family history of psychosis","C":"9-year-old child with ADHD and treatment-emergent tics","D":"19-year-old with signifi cant residual symptoms of ADHD","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Treatment-emergent tics and dyskinesias are often self-limited over 7 to 10 days in children taking stimulants. In some cases, if the severity of tics necessitates a dose reduction, adjustments can be made in the medication dosage. In severe cases, atomoxetine could be prescribed after stopping stimulants. Methylphenidate may also worsen already existing tics in one-third of patients. In most of these cases tics are variable, depending on the plasma levels. They resolve immediately on clearance of the drug. In the rest, tics are triggered by the treatment and persist for several months. It is appropriate to continue treating an adult with residual, disabling symptoms of ADHD. Though stimulants can exacerbate psychosis, a family history of psychosis is not a contraindication. Family history of ADHD does not adversely infl uence stimulant prescription. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 281.140 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which one of the following is not a dose-dependent side-effect of olanzapine?","options":{"A":"Agranulocytosis","B":"Akathisia","C":"Galactorrhoea","D":"Parkinsonism","E":"Sedation"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Olanzapine can induce agranulocytosis, similar to clozapine albeit at much lower frequency. Atypicality of atypical antipsychotics does not exist as a dichotomous entity from typical drugs. At high doses, most atypical agents lose their atypicality and produce extrapyramidal symptoms and galactorrhoea. Large weight gains with increased appetite occur during the fi rst 6 months of treatment, irrespective of the dose used. The risk of weight gain continues over time, probably reaching a peak after 9 months, after which it slows down but continues as long as one takes the drug. Weight gain is associated with increased total cholesterol. Olanzapine is also associated with dose-dependent sedation, though tolerance usually develops for this effect. Tolosa-Vilella C et al. Olanzapine-induced agranulocytosis: a case report and review of the literature. Progress in Neuro-psychopharmacology and Biological Psychiatry 2002; 26: 411–414."},{"question":"An anxious patient who has not responded to initial doses of clozapine titration wants to know about the dose-dependent side-effects of clozapine. Which one of the following is defi nitely not a dose-related risk?","options":{"A":"Seizures","B":"Hypersalivation","C":"Sedation","D":"Agranulocytosis","E":"Anticholinergic effects"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Agranulocytosis is not dose dependent; it is idiosyncratic. A reduction in dose of clozapine cannot help a patient who has developed agranulocytosis. Clozapine-associated seizures are clearly dose related. When doses of clozapine below 300 mg/day are used, the seizure rate remains 1%; further doses between 300 and 600 mg/day increase the seizure rate to 2.7%, and doses above 600 mg/day have a rate of 4.4%. Slower dose titration, using a lower dose, and the addition of anticonvulsant agent such as valproic acid can reduce the frequency of seizures. Anticholinergic effects, such as tachycardia and constipation, may be dose dependent, and are often noted in overdoses. Similar to sialorrhoea, clozapine-related tachycardia is often seen in early phases of treatment, and tolerance develops in due course. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, pp. 71, 73, and 81."},{"question":"Acetyl cholinesterase and butyryl cholinesterase are two enzymes metabolizing acetylcholine. Which one of the following antidementia drugs has signifi cant effects on both enzymes?","options":{"A":"Galantamine","B":"Rivastigmine","C":"Ginkgo biloba","D":"Memantine","E":"Donepezil"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Donepezil and galantamine are selective inhibitors of acetylcholinesterase enzyme. Rivastigmine affects both butyryl and acetyl cholinesterase. Galantamine also affects nicotinic receptors. However, these differences do not translate into signifi cant clinical differences in effi cacy or tolerability. Memantine is an N-methyl-D-aspartic acid (NMDA) antagonist and hence is thought to be a neuroprotective agent. Tacrine was one of the foremost anticholinesterases introduced but is no longer used due to hepatotoxic effects. Tacrine inhibits both acetyl and butyrylcholinesterases. Ginkgo biloba is widely used in Germany as a cognitive enhancer. Its mechanism of action is unclear. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 415. Leonard BE. Pharmacotherapy in the treatment of Alzheimer’s disease: an update. World Psychiatry 2004; 3: 84–88."},{"question":"A 66-year-old lady being treated for tremors by her neurologist develops insomnia, increased nocturnal myoclonus, and disruptive nightmares following the prescription of a particular medication. The most likely causative agent is","options":{"A":"Bromocriptine","B":"Levodopa","C":"Propranolol","D":"Pramipexole","E":"Selegeline"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Levodopa is used to treat symptoms of Parkinson’s disease. Levodopa is associated with increase in libido; in some cases secondary mania is reported. It can cause disruptive nightmares and forced reminiscences. It is a stimulating medication and can produce initial insomnia and nocturnal myoclonus. It is also associated with belpharospasms. Bromocriptine and pramipexole are dopamine agonists while selegeline is a monoamine oxidase B (MAO-B) inhibitor used in treating Parkinson’s disease. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 410.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 141"},{"question":"A patient treated for severe Parkinson’s disease develops troublesome psychotic symptoms attributed to levodopa. The neurologist is reluctant to reduce or stop levodopa given her deterioration in the past when this was attempted. The most appropriate drug to treat her psychotic symptoms is","options":{"A":"Olanzapine","B":"Risperidone","C":"Quetiapine","D":"Paliperidone","E":"Bromocriptine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Psychosis is common in patients with Parkinson’s disease. This may be due to the use of dopaminergic medications such as levodopa or unrelated to the pathology of Parkinson’s disease. Lewy body dementia can result in psychotic features and prominent parkinsonism, in which case antipsychotic treatment may be required. In such cases and in levodopa-induced psychosis, quetiapine has been used as the treatment of choice as it has a very low extrapyramidal side- effects profi le. Clozapine is also equally useful and generally regarded as the gold standard. In Parkinson’s disease-related psychosis even low doses of atypical antipsychotics can result in good effi cacy. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 411."},{"question":"Which one of the following drugs denatures the monoamine oxidase enzyme, rendering it ineffective to metabolize even low amounts of tyramine?","options":{"A":"Selegiline","B":"Moclobemide","C":"Tranylcypromine","D":"Reboxetine","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Tyramine is predominantly metabolized by MAO-A enzyme present in gut wall and liver, apart from brain and other tissues. Drugs which irreversibly inhibit MAO-A affect tyramine metabolism. These include tranylcypromine and phenelzine. Drugs such as selegiline are irreversible MAO-B selective inhibitors; they do not have the same effect on tyramine as MAO-A inhibitors. Moclobemide is a reversible, somewhat competitive MAO-A selective inhibitor. Thus, when the relative amount of tyramine in the vicinity increases, the moclobemide molecule makes way for tyramine from the MAO-A enzyme site. Reboxetine is not an MAO inhibitor. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 2855."},{"question":"Tyramine is present in certain food substances and can cause hypertensive crises if consumed by a patient on monoamine oxidase inhibitors. Choose the site of action of tyramine from the following options","options":{"A":"Presynaptic storage vesicles","B":"Reuptake channels","C":"α1 adrenergic receptors","D":"β adrenergic receptors","E":"α2 autoreceptors"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Tyramine is a monoamine naturally occurring in many food substances. Generally, most ingested tyramine undergoes a complete breakdown in the periphery due to the action of MAO-A enzyme in gut mucosa and liver. When a patient is taking MAO-A inhibitor drugs, tyramine escapes such degradation and enters the brain through amino acid transport. It uses the norepinephrine reuptake channels, and gains entry to presynaptic neurones. Here, tyramine stimulates release of all bound monoamines, especially norepinephrine, leading to a hypertensive reaction. This is called the cheese reaction as tyramine is abundant in mature cheeses. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 2860."},{"question":"Which one of the following antidepressants can block the neuronal uptake of tyramine and potentially reduce the risk of tyramine–MAOI interaction?","options":{"A":"SSRIs","B":"Moclobemide","C":"L-tryptophan","D":"Tricyclic antidepressants","E":"Levothyroxine"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"As tyramine gains entry to presynaptic neurones via the norepinephrine transporter, blocking this reuptake transporter can prevent tyramine action, at least theoretically. Tricyclic antidepressants act via blockade of this transporter. Hence the incidence of cheese reaction due to tyramine is less in those who are on tricyclic antidepressants before the commencement of MAO-A inhibitors. However, such combination is not advisable as the potential to cause serotonin syndrome is very high. SSRIs and L-tryptophan can increase the risk of serotonin syndrome many fold when coprescribed with MAO-A inhibitors. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 2965. White K and Simpson G. Combined MAOI-tricyclic antidepressant treatment: a re-evaluation. Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology 1981; 1: 264–282.142 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which one of the following mood stabilizers can potentiate GABA transmission by increasing GABA release, reducing GABA metabolism, and increasing GABA receptor density?","options":{"A":"Lithium","B":"Carbamazepine","C":"Lamotrigine","D":"Valproate","E":"Vigabatrin"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The mechanism of action of lithium remains speculative. Valproate increases gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) release and reduces GABA metabolism. It increases neuronal responsiveness to GABA and also increases GABA receptor density. Carbamazepine B prolongs sodium channel inactivation, leading to a secondary increase in calcium channel inactivation. This is linked to reduced glutamatergic neurotransmission. Carbamazepine also has adenosine antagonistic properties. Lamotrigine acts via membrane stabilization while vigabatrin is a GABA transaminase inhibitor. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 2757."},{"question":"Which one of the following benzodiazepines has partial agonistic action at some receptors, leading to fewer withdrawal symptoms?","options":{"A":"Diazepam","B":"Triazolam","C":"Lorazepam","D":"Clonazepam","E":"Chlordiazepoxide"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Clonazepam has partial agonistic action at certain benzodiazepine receptors, leading to fewer withdrawal symptoms. Clonazepam is a high-potency drug (0.25 mg clonazepam is equated to 5 mg diazepam); it is shown to be effective in panic disorder and social phobia (but is not recommended for long-term therapy). In bipolar type 1 disorder, clonazepam may result in a prolonged remission phase and reduced depressive relapses when used as an adjuvant to lithium or lamotrigine, respectively. Haefely W et al. Novel anxiolytics that act as partial agonists at benzodiazepine receptors. Trends in Pharmacological Science 1990; 11: 452–456."},{"question":"A patient presents with recurrent episodes of feeling detached and unreal. A pharmacological agent that can worsen the above symptoms is","options":{"A":"Clozapine","B":"Caffeine","C":"Lamotrigine","D":"Clonazepam","E":"Valproate"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Caffeine can worsen depersonalization. Experimental induction of depersonalization and derealization has been tried using caffeine. SSRIs are used in treating established cases of depersonalization disorder. However, paradoxically, some times initiation or discontinuation of SSRIs can produce depersonalization experiences. Lamotrigine and clonazepam are used in treating symptoms of depersonalization. Medford N et al. Understanding and treating depersonalization disorder. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2005; 11: 92–100."},{"question":"A 64-year-old man with schizophrenia is being treated for cirrhotic liver. Unfortunately, he develops a relapse of psychotic symptoms and needs a change in his antipsychotic prescription. The safest option with regard to his hepatic status is","options":{"A":"Amisulpride","B":"Olanzapine","C":"Clozapine","D":"Risperidone","E":"Chlorpromazine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Most psychotropic medications undergo hepatic metabolism. Notable exceptions are amisulpride, paliperidone, lithium, acamprosate, and gabapentin. These medications are largely renally excreted without much hepatic degradation. Hence in patients with hepatic failure, the antipsychotic of choice from the given list is amisulpride. Note that certain benzodiazepines, such as oxazepam, undergo glucuronide conjugation (phase 2 metabolism) reaction but no oxidation (phase 1 metabolism) in the liver. Oxazepam can be used in treating alcohol withdrawal in a patient with signifi cantly low hepatic reserve. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 404."},{"question":"The mechanism of action of St John’s wort is","options":{"A":"Serotonin antagonism","B":"Norepinephrine agonism","C":"MAO inhibition","D":"Multiple reuptake inhibition","E":"Membrane stabilization"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"St John’s wort has been shown to be an effective antidepressant in mild to moderate cases. It increases photosensitivity of skin but other adverse effects are limited. It is thought to act by inhibiting reuptake of multiple monoamines, including serotonin, norepinephrine, and dopamine. It also inhibits GABA and glutamate reuptake but the effects of these are unknown. It is a potent inducer of hepatic CYP450 enzymes, leading to a fall in plasma levels of carbamazepine, oral contraceptives, and warfarin if coprescribed. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 244."},{"question":"Which one of the following acts via opiate receptors and could be a potential agent to prevent relapse of alcohol use?","options":{"A":"Naloxone","B":"Acamprosate","C":"Disulfi ram","D":"Naltrexone","E":"Bupropion"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Opioid receptor antagonists are tested as adjuncts for the treatment of alcohol dependence. They can reduce alcohol craving and alcohol consumption. If naltrexone is used in maintaining abstinence, the number of relapses is reduced and the severity of relapses, if they occur, is considerably less. Naloxone is a parenterally administered opioid antagonist, used to reverse the effects of exogenously administered opioids. Acamprosate, bupropion, and disulfi ram do not act via an opioid mechanism. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 332.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 143"},{"question":"A 44-year-old man with bipolar disorder treated with lithium develops chronic back pain. His GP wants to prescribe a NSAID analgesic and asks you to choose a NSAID with the least potential to interact with lithium. You will choose","options":{"A":"Ibuprofen","B":"Diclofenac","C":"Aspirin","D":"Ketorolac","E":"Indomethacin"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Aspirin (and sulindac, to some extent) has comparatively lesser potential to interact with lithium compared to most other NSAIDs. NSAIDs can reduce renal lithium clearance via their effects on fl uid balance. This can lead to renal toxicity if the coadministration is suffi ciently long. Indometacin is suspected to be worse compared to other NSAIDs in this regard, though careful monitoring of lithium levels is warranted even with use of COX-2 inhibitors such as rofecoxib. Lithium excretion is decreased by medications such as thiazides, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, and, to a lesser extent, frusemide (furosemide). Lithium clearance is increased by other medications with diuretic effects such as acetazolamide, mannitol, and caffeine. Reimann IW, Diener U, and Frölich JC. Indomethacin but not aspirin increases plasma lithium ion levels. Archives of General Psychiatry 1983; 40: 283–286."},{"question":"Stimulants are useful in ADHD. The symptom that best responds to stimulants is","options":{"D":"Motor tics","A":"Insomnia","B":"Hyperactivity","C":"Inattention","E":"Conduct disturbance"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Stimulants such as methylphenidate are more effective in treating hyperactivity than inattention due to ADHD. Methylphenidate is available in two forms—immediate release and sustained release forms. The immediate release form starts to act within 20 to 60 minutes after administration and acts for up to 2 to 4 hours, while the sustained release form acts up to 12 hours, obviating the need for divided doses. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 281."},{"question":"Atomoxetine is useful in children with ADHD. The mechanism of action is by","options":{"D":"Membrane stabilization","A":"Norepinephrine reuptake inhibition","B":"Serotonin potentiation","C":"GABA potentiation","E":"Acetylcholine synthesis"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Atomoxetine is the fi rst non-stimulant drug to be approved for ADHD. It has a tricyclic- like structure; it is classifi ed as a phenylpropanolamine derivative. It acts through selective inhibition of the presynaptic norepinephrine transporter. It has a half-life of approximately 5 hours and is metabolized through the CYP2D6 pathway. Drugs such as fl uoxetine, paroxetine or bupropion are CYP2D6 inhibitors and may raise atomoxetine levels. Atomoxetine is used for patients who fi nd stimulants too activating or who experience other intolerable side-effects. Atomoxetine has been associated with cases of severe liver injury in a few patients. It must be avoided in patients taking MAOI. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1103."},{"question":"A 30-year-old known heroin user is brought to A&E after an overdose of heroin, with a GCS of 3, a respiratory rate of four breaths per minute, and pinpoint pupils. On administration of naloxone he develops running nose, diarrhoea and profuse sweating, and multiple joint aches. The most likely explanation is","options":{"A":"Residual symptoms of toxicity","B":"Allergic reaction to naloxone","C":"Effect of coadministered cocaine","D":"Precipitated opioid withdrawal","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Naloxone is an opioid antagonist. It can precipitate acute withdrawal when administered to patients who are actively taking opioid drugs. Symptoms of acute opioid withdrawal include a strong urge to seek the drug, feeling of temperature change, pain, and abdominal distress. Patient may also have confusion, drowsiness, vomiting, and diarrhoea. When opioid antagonists that act for a long duration, such as naltrexone, are prescribed to encourage abstinence and maintain remission in opioid users it is absolutely essential that the use of street drugs has been completely stopped for at least a period of 5 to 7 days. If not, acute withdrawal symptoms will be precipitated. Naloxone produces opioid antagonism that lasts less than 1 hour, whereas naltrexone-induced withdrawal can persist for more than 24 hours. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1076."},{"question":"A 30-year-old known heroin user develops opioid intoxication which reverses on administration of naloxone. He takes a self-discharge against medical advice. He was brought back within a few hours of this self-discharge with signs suggestive of opioid intoxication, but without any history of additional opioid intake. The most likely explanation is","options":{"A":"Inappropriate dose of naloxone","B":"Inappropriate route of administration of naloxone","C":"Short half-life of naloxone","D":"Reduced opioid tolerance on administering naloxone","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Naloxone produces opioid antagonism that lasts less than 1 hour, as its plasma half- life is between 1 and 2 hours. In opioid overdose, naloxone is administered intravenously and repeated at 2- to 3-minute intervals until the desired response is achieved. In order to maintain recovery in signifi cant overdoses, it is often necessary to continue naloxone by infusion or repeated administration. As this has not happened in the patient described in this question, signs of intoxication have returned. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1339.144 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Naloxone can be life-saving in cases of opioid toxicity. The commonest route of administration of naloxone for this purpose is","options":{"A":"Subcutaneous","B":"Intramuscular","C":"Transtracheal","D":"Intrathecal","E":"Intravenous"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Naloxone is commonly administered via intravenous injections in the UK. It can also be administered intramuscularly or via subcutaneous injections. Wanger K, Brough L, Macmillan I et al. Intravenous vs. subcutaneous naloxone for out-of-hospital management of presumed opioid overdose. Academic Emergency Medicine 1998; 5: 293–299."},{"question":"Lofexidine is useful in managing symptoms of opiate withdrawal. The mechanism of action of lofexidine is by","options":{"A":"Agonism of α autoreceptors 2","B":"Direct opioid antagonism","C":"Partial opioid agonism","D":"Direct dopamine blockade","E":"Spinal opiate receptor blockade"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Lofexidine is an analogue of clonidine, and licensed only in the UK for use in opiate detoxifi cation. It is an α adrenoceptor agonist, similar to clonidine but it causes signifi cantly less 2 hypotension. Action of lofexidine peaks at 3 hours and its elimination half-life is 12–15 hours. It is administered in divided doses to achieve the desired peak effect coincidental with the peak of withdrawal effects. It is used for 1 to 3 weeks in opiate detoxifi cation, with or without substituting a tapering dose of prescribed opiates. α agonism leads to increased autoreceptor 2 activity and resultant reduction in sympathetic stimulation, which mediates the withdrawal symptoms when administration of opioids is suddenly stopped. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1340."},{"question":"Fluoxetine increases the clinical effi cacy of clozapine through which of the following pharmacokinetic mechanism?","options":{"A":"Increased plasma protein binding","B":"Increased intestinal absorption","C":"Inhibition of hepatic metabolism","D":"Reduced renal clearance","E":"Improved blood–brain barrier penetration"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"SSRIs, especially fl uoxetine, inhibit CYP2D6 enzyme involved in the metabolism of clozapine. This results in an increase in clozapine levels, leading to additional therapeutic advantage. This combination strategy has been tried in patients whose psychotic symptoms are refractory to clozapine. Therapeutic use of this interaction should be considered only when compliance is assured, maximal dosing has been achieved, and despite this the serum level is below 350 ng/ml. It should be attempted cautiously and with regular monitoring of plasma levels. When adding an SSRI, the dose of clozapine should be reduced in anticipation of the likely rise in plasma concentrations—an approximately twofold dose reduction is suggested for fl uoxetine and paroxetine. Williams L, Newton G, Roberts K et al. Clozapine-resistant schizophrenia: a positive approach. British Journal of Psychiatry 2002; 181: 184–187."},{"question":"Tyramine can produce the ‘cheese reaction’ in patients taking MAO inhibitors. Which one of the following is true with respect to the moclobemide–tyramine interaction?","options":{"A":"Moclobemide does not cause cheese reaction with tyramine","B":"Moclobemide causes cheese reaction at the same frequency as phenelzine","C":"Moclobemide does not act on the same enzyme that metabolizes tyramine","D":"Large consumption of tyramine can produce the cheese reaction with moclobemide","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Moclobemide acts on the same MAO-A enzyme that metabolizes tyramine, but the effect of moclobemide on this enzyme is reversible, leading to a lesser propensity of moclobemide to cause the tyramine reaction. When an unusually large consumption of tyramine- containing products occurs, moclobemide can produce the cheese reaction similar to other MAO inhibitors. Due to the reversible and partly competitive nature of MAO-A blockade by moclobemide, normal activity of existing MAO-A returns within 16 to 48 hours of the last dose of moclobemide. Therefore, the dietary restrictions are less stringent, reducing the avoidance of foods with a high concentrations of tyramine to a period from 1 hour before to 2 hours after taking moclobemide. These foods must be avoided only for 3 days after the last dose of moclobemide, unlike other MAO inhibitors where several days of diet is needed even after withdrawing the medication. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1068."},{"question":"Which one of the following is a partial opioid agonist with a low intrinsic activity?","options":{"A":"Naloxone","B":"Naltrexone","C":"Methadone","D":"Buprenorphine","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Buprenorphine is a partial µ-opioid agonist. It has a slow onset of action and dissociates rather slowly from the µ-receptor. It has very poor oral bioavailability and so is administered sublingually. The half-life of buprenorphine is only 3 to 5 hours but its action is rather prolonged due to slow dissociation of the drug molecule from the receptor—this phase lasts for more than 24 hours. Due to its partial agonistic action, the propensity to cause respiratory depression is lower than that of heroin. When overdose occurs, naloxone must be given at a higher dose and in continuous infusion to reverse the toxicity. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1338.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 145"},{"question":"A 12-year-old child treated for ADHD with stimulants develops tics, which persist even on withdrawal of stimulants. Which of the following offers a potential to treat both tics and ADHD symptoms simultaneously?","options":{"A":"Clonidine","B":"Lofexidine","C":"Bromocriptine","D":"Atomoxetine","E":"Risperidone"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Clonidine is a central α agonist. As the α receptor is an autoreceptor, which on 2 2 stimulation reduces sympathetic output, clonidine acts as sympatholytic drug. It is useful in some patients with tics and in Tourette’s syndrome. As many drug withdrawal states are mediated by sympathetic overdrive, clonidine can potentially be used in opioid, alcohol, or benzodiazepine withdrawal though this is not a licensed indication. In children with ADHD, clonidine can be used as a third-line agent after stimulants and atomoxetine. However, it is rarely used for pure ADHD symptoms; it is commonly used when ADHD is accompanied by motor tics. Clonidine can cause signifi cant hypotension. Tourette’s Syndrome Study Group. Treatment of ADHD in children with tics. A randomized controlled trial. Neurology 2002; 58: 527–536."},{"question":"A 40-year-old male develops impotence secondary to antidepressant therapy. After trying various options, you are considering sildenafi l. The mechanism of action of sildenafi l is by","options":{"A":"Phosphodiesterase inhibition","B":"Acetylcholine stimulation","C":"Increasing nitric oxide production","D":"Blockade of sympathetic discharge","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Sexual arousal in a man results in the release of nitric oxide (NO) in vascular endothelium, mediated by autonomic nervous signals. NO acts as a second messenger and stimulates the synthesis of cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP). This initiates a chain reaction, which results in corpus cavernosal relaxation and an increase in blood fl ow into the penis. This is followed by erection. Once produced, cGMP is cleared by the action of an intracellular enzyme called phosphodiesterase-5 (PDE-5). When PDE-5 is inhibited, the concentration of cGMP increases intracellularly, leading to prolonged tumescence and turgidity of the penis. Hence sexual arousal is required for PDE-5 inhibitors to have an effect on performance. Sildenafi l acts as a PDE-5 inhibitor, allowing an increase in cGMP and enhancing the vasodilatory effects of NO. Hence it is sometimes referred to as an NO enhancer, but it does not have a direct effect on NO synthesis. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1078."},{"question":"Buspirone is an anxiolytic with no immediate effect on acute administration, unlike diazepam. This is due to","options":{"A":"Short half-life of buspirone","B":"Longer time required to achieve steady state","C":"Buspirone follows fi rst-order kinetics","D":"Buspirone is a GABA partial agonist","E":"Buspirone acts via the serotonin system"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Buspirone is an azapirone which, by partial agonistic action on the 5-HT receptor, 1A suppresses activity in presynaptic serotonergic neurones. This in turn reduces the serotonin activity, leading to down-regulation of various 5-HT receptors. This is related to anxiolytic activity but with no hypnotic effect. Though buspirone is equieffective to diazepam, patients taking buspirone improve more slowly. This is related to the inherent mode of action, which depends on receptor down-regulation rather than producing a direct receptor action. Patients who are switched from benzodiazepines to buspirone do not do as well as those without previous exposure to benzodiazepines. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1289."},{"question":"Most diuretics interact with lithium to produce signifi cant changes in plasma lithium levels. Which one of the following diuretics is useful in treating polyuria, a common side-effect of lithium?","options":{"A":"Amiloride","B":"Triamterene","C":"Chlorthiazide","D":"Frusemide","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Amiloride is useful in some cases of lithium-induced polyuria. Polyuria is the most common adverse effect of lithium, occurring in 25% of patients. This polyuria is related to the antagonistic effects of lithium on antidiuretic hormone, leading to diuresis. Conservative management includes fl uid replacement, decreasing the dosage of lithium, and single daily dosing of lithium. Potassium-sparing diuretics, such as triamterene and amiloride, or thiazide diuretics are also useful. Unlike thiazides and frusemide, amiloride does not reduce lithium clearance; instead it may increase lithium excretion. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1059.146 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"A 30-year-old woman was diagnosed with paranoid schizophrenia. She has been hospitalized and is prescribed antipsychotics. Which one of the following treatment-emergent conditions is known to be associated with the risk of suicide?","options":{"A":"Akathisia","B":"Anticholinergic symptoms","C":"Dystonia of the laryngeal muscles","D":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","E":"Tardive dyskinesia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Akathisia is the commonest movement disorder associated with antipsychotic prescription. It is more commonly acute, with onset within 48 to 96 hours of administration of the antipsychotics. It is unclear whether akathisia results from dopamine antagonism or dysfunction of other neurotransmitters such as serotonin, acetyl choline, and norepinephrine. Akathisia is often mistaken for anxiety or worsening of psychotic agitation. Akathisia can vary in severity over time, making assessment diffi cult. Akathisia is associated with suicidality, absconsion, aggression, and non-compliance. Tardive dyskinesia develops late in the course of antipsychotic treatment and as such is not associated with absconsion from in-patient units, as more often than not the patients do not recognize having troublesome movement disorders. Neuroleptic malignant syndrome and laryngeal dystonia are life-threatening syndromes, often requiring immediate medical attention. Hansen L. A critical review of akathisia—and its possible association with suicidal behaviour. Human Psychopharmacology 2001; 16: 495–505."},{"question":"For typical neuroleptics, the antipsychotic effect on positive psychotic symptoms is strongly correlated with","options":{"A":"D2 occupancy","B":"Half-life","C":"D4 occupancy","D":"5-HT antagonism","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"D2 occupancy in typical antipsychotics correlates with their antipsychotic effi cacy and propensity to cause extrapyramidal side-effects. This was demonstrated in a landmark positron emission tomography (PET) study by Kapur et al., where haloperidol produced therapeutic effect at around 65% occupancy; extrapyramidal side-effects occurred when the occupancy was around 78%. For atypicals, both 5-HT blockade and D2 occupancy are correlated with clinical 2A effi cacy. Clozapine and quetiapine occupy less than half of D2 receptors but still are effi cacious as antipsychotics. Jones MM and Pilowsky LS. Dopamine and antipsychotic drug action revisited. British Journal of Psychiatry 2002; 181: 271."},{"question":"Memantine is an antidementia drug licensed for moderately severe Alzheimer’s dementia. The mechanism by which memantine acts is","options":{"A":"Inhibition of NMDA receptor","B":"Inhibition of calcium ion channels","C":"Stimulation of GABA output","D":"Stimulation of glutamate release","E":"Mimicking the effects of acetylcholine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Memantine has moderate affi nity for the NMDA receptor and acts as a voltage- dependent and non-competitive antagonist. Calcium-mediated excitotoxicity could be due to overstimulation of NMDA receptors by glutamate. Memantine may protect cells against excess glutamate by partially blocking NMDA receptors associated with abnormal transmission of glutamate, while physiological transmission remains unaffected. Johnstone E et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 303."},{"question":"Phenytoin and lithium are said to have narrow therapeutic indices. The term therapeutic index refers to","options":{"A":"Ratio between median toxic and median effective dose","B":"Rate of production of toxic effects at a constant dose","C":"Duration of persistence of toxic effects after the onset","D":"Proportion of patients who experience a specifi c side-effect","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Therapeutic index is a measure that relates the dose of a drug required to produce a desired effect to that which produces an undesired effect. In animal studies, the therapeutic index is usually defi ned as the ratio of the median toxic dose to the median effective dose for some therapeutically relevant effect. The therapeutic index of a drug in humans cannot be measured directly and the value itself does not have much clinical use; instead, drug trials often reveal a range of usually effective doses and a range of possibly toxic doses, from which a safe therapeutic range is determined, for example 1.0 to 1.2 for lithium which when exceeded results in toxic effects. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 2685.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 147"},{"question":"The lower incidence of extrapyramidal side-effects due to clozapine compared to haloperidol is possibly related to","options":{"A":"Duration of D2 receptor occupancy","B":"Glutamate blockade","C":"GABA release at basal ganglia","D":"Intrinsic partial agonistic activity at the D2 receptor","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Clozapine has a hit-and-run profi le at D2 receptors. The occupancy is around 40% and the time course of occupancy is comparatively shorter than typical antipsychotics. Quetiapine has a similar mode of action to that of clozapine. Clozapine and quetiapine bind more loosely to D2 receptors than dopamine itself whereas haloperidol and risperidone bind to these receptors more tightly. It is suggested that antipsychotics with low binding affi nity and fast dissociation rates, such as clozapine and quetiapine, are more responsive to endogenous changes in dopamine than those that bind more tightly and dissociate from the receptor more slowly. This is because baseline dopamine levels are interspersed with task- or stress-induced, several-fold increases in dopamine from normal physiological level. Pani L, Pira L, and Marchese G. Antipsychotic effi cacy: Relationship to optimal D2-receptor occupancy. European Psychiatry 2007; 22: 267–275."},{"question":"The volume of distribution of a drug depends on all of the following except","options":{"A":"Protein binding","B":"Lipid solubility","C":"Tissue binding","D":"Half-life","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Volume of distribution is a measure of the apparent space in the body available to contain an administered drug. It can be calculated as a ratio of the administered dose (intravenous) and plasma (or blood) concentration at time = 0, that is when administration occurred. Hence, the higher the plasma concentration, the lower the volume of distribution and vice versa. Volume of distribution can vastly exceed any physical volume in the body because it is an apparent, not an actual, volume necessary to contain a drug homogeneously at the concentration found in the plasma. Drugs with very high volumes of distribution have higher concentrations in extravascular tissue than in the vascular compartment, while those that are contained fully in the vascular compartment have a smaller volume of distribution limited by the volume of plasma component. The apparent volume of distribution depends on properties of the drug molecule, such as lipid solubility and protein binding. Tissue binding decreases the plasma concentration and makes the apparent volume larger. Plasma protein binding increases plasma concentration and makes the apparent volume smaller. Half-life is a secondary measurement calculated from the volume of distribution and clearance rates, but volume of distribution itself does not depend on half-life of a drug. If the rate of clearance is slower or the volume of distribution is more extensive, the half-life will be longer. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 8th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2004, p. 2702."},{"question":"Drug A is an anticonvulsant, metabolized to inactive metabolites by the CYP450 system. Drug B, which induces CYP450, is expected to produce which one of the following if coadministered with drug A?","options":{"A":"Reduced concentration of inactive metabolites","B":"Reduced effi cacy of drug A","C":"Increased metabolism of drug A resulting in increased effi cacy","D":"Increased concentration of drug A in plasma","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The cytochrome P450 (CYP450) enzyme system is responsible for much of the phase 1 metabolism of drugs. Phase 1 metabolism includes oxidation, reduction, and hydrolysis, as a result of which a molecule (active or inactive) suitable for conjugation is produced. The phase 2 metabolism involves conjugation reactions such as glucuronidation, as a result of which polar compounds (mostly inactive), which are excretable in bile or urine, are formed. Induction and inhibition of the activity of the CYP450 system can result in various potential drug interactions. The most important enzymes in the CYP family involved in the metabolism of psychotropic drugs are CYP1A2, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, and CYP3A4. CYP3A4 is responsible for the metabolism of more than 90% of psychotropic drugs that undergo hepatic biotransformation. In this question, if the CYP system is induced then the metabolic breakdown of drug A will be increased, producing more inactive metabolites. This will reduce the effi cacy of drug A. Chadwick B, Waller DG, and Edwards JG et al. Potentially hazardous drug interactions with psychotropics. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2005; 11: 440–449.148 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Glucuronyl transferase acts on an antidepressant drug A and converts it into a more water-soluble component with less potency but a higher concentration in bile. This process is called","options":{"A":"Conjugation","B":"Oxidation","C":"Saponifi cation","D":"Depolarization","E":"Enzyme induction"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Conjugation refers to phase 2 metabolism of administered drugs. These take place after oxidation-type reactions in phase 1. Enzymes such as transferases carry out conjugation, which usually results in inactive metabolites (or, rarely, active compounds, e.g. morphine). It is not essential that a drug must undergo phase 1 metabolism in order to undergo phase 2 metabolism, for example oxazepam undergoes direct phase 2 reactions. Cookson J et al., eds. Use of Drugs in Psychiatry: The Evidence from Psychopharmacology, 5th edn. Gaskell, 2002, p. 57."},{"question":"Metabolism of psychotropic drugs include phase 1 and phase 2 reactions. All of the following are phase 2 reactions except","options":{"A":"Glucuronidation","B":"Methylation","C":"Oxidation","D":"N acetylation","E":"Sulfation"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Oxidation is not a phase 2 reaction—it is a phase 1 reaction. Various types of phase 2 reactions include glucuronidation, acetylation, sulfation, and glutathione conjugation. Hydrolysis and hydroxylation are considered to be other phase 1 reactions. Cookson J et al., eds. Use of Drugs in Psychiatry: The Evidence from Psychopharmacology, 5th edn. Gaskell, 2002, p. 57."},{"question":"Breastfeeding is contraindicated when certain psychotropics are administered. The characteristic features of such psychotropics that are secreted in breast milk include all except","options":{"A":"High lipid solubility","B":"High degree of ionization","C":"Poor protein binding","D":"Low acidic property","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Most prescribed drugs transfer into breast milk except very large molecules such as heparin and insulin, but the amount transferred is negligent for most drugs. The mechanism of transfer is passive diffusion through the lipid cell membrane of the lactating glands. Factors such as low plasma protein binding and high lipid solubility aid a drug in reaching high concentrations in breast milk. As milk is slightly more acidic than plasma, weakly basic drugs transfer more readily into breast milk, become ionized in the acid medium, and so get ‘trapped’. Unionized molecules cross biological membranes more easily than charged particles (ions). If a breastfeeding mother must take psychotropics and the drug is a relatively safe one, it is recommended that the drug is taken 30–60 minutes after nursing and 3–4 hours before the next feed, if possible. Cohen D. Psychotropic medication and breast feeding. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2005; 11: 371–379."},{"question":"A 25-year-old postgraduate student is suffering from initial insomnia during his fi nal year of study. He is asking for a hypnotic that will cause least disturbance to his sleep architecture. The best choice is","options":{"A":"Diazepam","B":"Chloral hydrate","C":"Zolpidem","D":"Promethiazine","E":"Temazepam"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Zolpidem is a non-benzodiazepine hypnotic of the imidazopyridine class. It is rapidly absorbed and has a short elimination half-life (mean 2.5 hours). It decreases sleep-onset latency, reduces disruptive midnight awakenings but has less consistent effects on total sleep time. It does not affect the REM distribution and unlike benzodiazepines, which increase stage 2 NREM at the expense of deep sleep NREM, zolpidem does not increase stage 2. It is unclear if zolpidem produces clinically signifi cant rebound as yet but dependence is thought to be low compared to other hypnotics. Darcourt G, Pringuey D, Sallière D, and Lavoisy J. The safety and tolerability of zolpidem—an update. Journal of Psychopharmacology 1999; 13: 81–93."},{"question":"Selegiline is used as an antiparkinsonian agent. Its mechanism of action is","options":{"A":"Dopamine receptor agonism","B":"Increased dopamine synthesis","C":"COMT inhibition","D":"MAO-A inhibition","E":"MAO-B inhibition"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Two types of monoamine oxidase have been recognized: monoamine oxidase A predominantly metabolizes norepinephrine and serotonin; monoamine oxidase B predominantly metabolizes dopamine. Selegiline is a selective inhibitor of monoamine oxidase B that retards the breakdown of dopamine and so it prolongs the antiparkinsonism effect of levodopa as an adjunctive therapy for patients with fl uctuating response to levodopa. Some studies have found it to be effective for treating depression but only at very high doses at which selective MAO-B inhibition effect is taken over by non-specifi c inhibition. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1070.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 149"},{"question":"Which of the following antidepressants is most selectively serotonergic?","options":{"A":"Fluoxetine","B":"Paroxetine","C":"Citalopram","D":"Clomipramine","E":"Venlafaxine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Citalopram (and escitalopram) is the most selective inhibitor of serotonin reuptake, with negligible effects on the reuptake of other monoamines such as norepinephrine or dopamine. It does not have any clinically signifi cant effect on histaminergic, GABAergic, or acetylcholinergic transmission. Paroxetine has clinically signifi cant anticholinergic activity. Fluoxetine weakly inhibits norepinephrine reuptake and binds to 5-HT receptors. Sertraline weakly inhibits both 2C norepinephrine and dopamine reuptake, without any additional clinical advantage. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1085."},{"question":"Which one of the following antipsychotics is strongly implicated in deaths due to QTc prolongation?","options":{"A":"Quetiapine","B":"Olanzapine","C":"Pimozide","D":"Risperidone","E":"Aripiprazole"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Prolongation of the QT interval of the ECG is associated with the development of torsade de pointes, a ventricular arrhythmia that can cause syncope and may progress to ventricular fi brillation and sudden death. The average QTc interval is approximately 400 ms. A QTc interval of 500 ms or greater is considered to be a high risk factor for torsades de pointes, though the prediction of arrhythmia is not simply linearly dependent on QT measure. An elevated risk of serious adverse cardiac events or sudden cardiac death has been documented for thioridazine, clozapine, droperidol, pimozide, and sertindole. These are considered higher-risk antipsychotics in terms of serious cardiac effects. Haloperidol, quetiapine, risperidone, chlorpromazine, and trifl uoperazine have a tendency to extend the QT interval even at therapeutic doses, but their link with sudden cardiac death is not yet clarifi ed. Amisulpride, aripiprazole, olanzapine, sulpride, and zotepine have not been linked with an elevated risk of sudden cardiac death or QTc prolongation. Typical neuroleptics that have lower potency, such as thioridazine and chlorpromazine, are more cardiotoxic than high-potency drugs such a haloperidol. The major effects on the electrocardiogram include prolongation of the QT and PR intervals, T wave blunting or inversion, and ST segment depression. Sudden death noted in antipsychotic recipients may also be due to seizures during sleep, sudden asphyxiation, temperature dysregulation (for example malignant hyperthermia), and neuroleptic malignant syndrome. Abdelmawla N and Mitchell AJ. Sudden cardiac death and antipsychotics. Part 2: Monitoring and prevention. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2006; 12: 100–109."},{"question":"Which one of the following anticonvulsants follows zero-order kinetics on dose increase within therapeutic range?","options":{"A":"Gabapentin","B":"Phenytoin","C":"Ethosuximide","D":"Valproate","E":"Lamotrigine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Drugs can undergo two different types of clearance when administered. When a constant fraction of a drug is cleared per unit time, it is called fi rst-order kinetics. This means that when the amount of drug in plasma or dose of administered drug increases, the clearance proportionately increases as a stable fraction of plasma concentration. When the system facilitating such clearance of drugs becomes saturated, drugs follow zero-order kinetics. Here a constant amount, not a fraction, of the drug is cleared per unit time. This means that irrespective of the amount of drug in plasma or dose of drug administered, only a fi xed unit of drug is cleared by the body. Thus, increasing the dose might result in serious toxicity in this case. Certain drugs have a propensity to undergo zero-order kinetics, even at therapeutic dose levels. Phenytoin metabolism is dose dependent, wherein smaller therapeutic doses follow fi rst-order kinetics while higher doses follow zero-order kinetics. Gabapentin is not metabolized by liver and undergoes fi rst-order renal clearance. Valproate follows fi rst-order kinetics even in wide therapeutic dose levels. Lamotrigine, too, shows fi rst-order linear kinetics and it is metabolized predominantly through glucuronidation. Splinter MY. Pharmacokinetic properties of new antiepileptic drugs. Journal of Pharmacy Practice 2005; 18: 444–460.150 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"A patient suffering from gastritis is prescribed several psychotropic medications. She wants to know which part of her body will absorb most of these orally administered drugs. The correct answer is","options":{"A":"Oral mucosa","B":"Large intestine","C":"Oesophagus","D":"Stomach","E":"Small intestine"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The small intestine has the largest surface area for drug absorption in the GI tract, and its membranes are more permeable than oral epithelium, oesophagus, or stomach. Hence most drugs are absorbed primarily in the small intestine. Gut mucosa harbours many metabolic enzymes that can breakdown active drug molecules and reduce the bioavailability of administered drugs. Atkinson A et al., eds. Principles of Clinical Pharmacology, 2nd edn. Elsevier, 2007, p. 39."},{"question":"A patient started on antidepressant treatment for a fi rst episode of depression stopped the medication abruptly after an initial response. Which one of the following medications, if prescribed, has the highest chance of causing the most troublesome discontinuation reaction?","options":{"A":"Mirtazapine","B":"Mianserin","C":"Fluoxetine","D":"Paroxetine","E":"Moclobemide"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The abrupt discontinuance of SSRI use is associated with a discontinuation syndrome. This is characterized by fatigue, light headedness, nausea, headache, anxiety, insomnia and poor concentration, fl u like symptoms, and electric shock-like paresthesias. In most cases, at least 6 weeks of treatment have elapsed before a discontinuation reaction takes place. The symptoms are self-resolving within 3 weeks in most cases. It is suggested that those who tolerate SSRIs poorly on initiation are more likely to develop discontinuation symptoms. Fluoxetine is the SSRI least likely to be associated with this syndrome, because it has a metabolite that is active with a half-life of more than a week. Shorter half-life medications, such as paroxetine, are associated with more discontinuation symptoms. Other classes of antidepressants, such as venlafaxine and tricyclics, are also associated with discontinuation reactions. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 240."},{"question":"A patient started on paroxetine after the fi rst episode of depression stopped the medication abruptly following an initial response. Apart from short half-life, higher incidence of discontinuation reaction following paroxetine is attributed to","options":{"A":"Cholinergic rebound","B":"Poor plasma protein binding","C":"High blood–brain barrier penetration","D":"Higher addictive potential","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Paroxetine has a half-life of nearly 21 hours, which is short compared to fl uoxetine, which has a prolonged duration of action due to an active metabolite that remains in the body for many days. In addition, paroxetine is more anticholinergic than most other SSRIs. Too rapid a discontinuation of any drug with signifi cant anticholinergic properties may lead to a cholinergic rebound. The symptoms are characterized by acetylcholine excess—nausea, vomiting sweating, stomach cramps, diarrhoea, anxiety, agitation, and insomnia. In some cases delirium can result. This rebound is more common with tricyclics than SSRIs, except in the case of paroxetine which has signifi cant anticholinergic effects. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 241."},{"question":"The tricyclic antidepressant which is most lethal on overdose is","options":{"A":"Dosulepin","B":"Imipramine","C":"Lofepramine","D":"Clomipramine","E":"Nortriptyline"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Dosulepin or dothiepin together with amitriptyline has been associated with most cases of fatal tricyclic antidepressant overdose. The ingestion of large quantities of tricyclics in overdose results in complex changes in the normal pharmacokinetics observed at therapeutic doses. Due to anticholinergic effects, gastric emptying is delayed and a sustained slow absorption takes place. Respiratory depression produces acidosis, which reduces protein binding and increases the active free fraction of the toxic drug. The toxic effects of tricyclics are due mainly to an increased sympathetic drive, adrenergic blockade, arrythmogenic effect on myocardium, and anticholinergic action. Kerr GW, McGuffi e AC, and Wilkie S. Tricyclic antidepressant overdose: a review. Emergency Medicine Journal 2001; 18: 236–241."},{"question":"A patient develops neuroleptic malignant syndrome secondary to antipsychotic prescription. Which one of the following properties of antipsychotics predicts a lower risk of producing neuroleptic malignant syndrome?","options":{"A":"High anticholinergic property","B":"High sedative effect","C":"Strong dopamine blockade","D":"α adrenergic blockade","E":"High potency"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Many treatment variables are associated as risk factors for neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS). Nearly all dopamine antagonists have been associated with NMS, although high-potency conventional antipsychotics are associated with a greater risk compared with low- potency agents and atypical antipsychotics. Intramuscular administration, rapid tranquilization, and faster titration rates are associated with higher incidence. Drugs with an intrinsic anticholinergic property have a lower propensity to cause NMS. Atypical agents produce atypical NMS, where the classic rigidity or hyperthermia component of NMS may be conspicuously absent. The risk of NMS is not related to α adrenergic blockade or sedative property of an antipsychotic drug. Stübner S, Rustenbeck E, Grohmann R et al. Severe and uncommon involuntary movement disorders due to psychotropic drugs. Pharmacopsychiatry 2004; 37 (Suppl. 1): S54–S64.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 151"},{"question":"Which one of the following agents produces dysphoria, myoclonus, fl u-like symptoms, ataxia, hyperacusis, and anxiety on withdrawal?","options":{"A":"Opioids","B":"Benzodiazepines","C":"Cannabis","D":"Procyclidine","E":"Amphetamines"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Benzodiazepine withdrawal symptoms include anxiety, inner tension, dizziness, insomnia, and anorexia. More severe withdrawal symptoms include nausea and vomiting, severe tremor, muscle weakness, postural hypotension, and tachycardia with psychological symptoms of dysphoria, depressive pessimistic thoughts, and obsessive ruminations. Myoclonus, pain symptoms, ataxia, kinaesthetic hallucinations, depersonalization, and hyperacusis are also noted. The withdrawal symptoms can develop after only 4 weeks of continuous use. Clonazepam, carbamazepine, and long-acting benzodiazepines themselves have been used in the management of withdrawal symptoms. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 264."},{"question":"Among antipsychotic agents, a high anticholinergic effect is noted for which one of the following pairs?","options":{"A":"Chlorpromazine and haloperidol","B":"Thioridazine and chlorpromazine","C":"Thioridazine and haloperidol","D":"Chlorpromazine and risperidone","E":"Risperidone and paliperidone"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Typical neuroleptics vary in their potential to cause anticholinergic symptoms. As a general rule, high-potency medications such as haloperidol produce less anticholinergic effects compared to low-potency drugs such as chlorpromazine and thioridazine. Peripheral anticholinergic effects include dry mouth, blurred vision, constipation, and urinary retention. Central anticholinergic effects, such as confusion and delirium, are seen especially in overdose of low-potency agents and in the elderly. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1048."},{"question":"Severe perspiration unrelated to ambient temperature is a side-effect associated with the prescription of","options":{"A":"SSRIs","B":"Venlafaxine","C":"TCAs","D":"All of the above","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Severe sweating incongruent to room temperature is associated with TCAs, SSRIs, and venlafaxine. This is a socially disabling side-effect. Drugs such as terazosin, cyproheptadine, benztropine, and oxybutynin have been tried anecdotally to treat this symptom but none of these has been recommended for routine use. The mechanism by which SSRIs increase sweating is unknown but is hypothesized to be through activation of the sympathetic nervous system or by action on the hypothalamus. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 983. Marcy R and Britton ML. Antidepressant-induced sweating. Annals of Pharmacotherapy 2005; 39: 748–752."},{"question":"A 55-year-old patient with late-onset schizophrenia develops dystonia on administration of antipsychotics. He is prescribed anticholinergic medications for this side-effect. Which one of the following anticholinergic drugs is most stimulating in its properties?","options":{"A":"Trihexyphenidyl","B":"Procyclidine","C":"Benztropine","D":"Biperiden","E":"Orphenadrine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The most commonly used anticholinergic drugs for extrapyramidal symptoms in patients taking antipsychotics are trihexyphenidyl (benzhexol), benztropine, biperiden, and procyclidine. Orphenadrine is an antihistaminergic agent with prominent anticholinergic action. Benztropine also has some antihistaminergic effects. All these agents are antimuscarinic. Trihexyphenidyl (benzhexol) is the most stimulating of all anticholinergics. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1004."},{"question":"A 55-year-old patient with late-onset schizophrenia develops dystonia on administration of antipsychotics. He is prescribed anticholinergic medications for this side-effect. Which one of the following anticholinergic drugs has the least abuse potential due to a relative lack of stimulating properties?","options":{"A":"Trihexyphenidyl","B":"Procyclidine","C":"Benztropine","D":"Biperiden","E":"Orphenadrine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Benztropine is the least stimulating anticholinergic agent and so it is least associated with drug-abuse potential. Benztropine reaches peak plasma concentrations in 2 to 3 hours after oral administration and acts for 1 to 12 hours. Benztropine is available as an intramuscular preparation and this is preferred when available in acute dystonia. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1004."},{"question":"A 55-year-old patient with late-onset schizophrenia develops dystonia on administration of antipsychotics. He is prescribed trihexyphenidyl for this side-effect. Which one of the following properties makes this drug most stimulating of all anticholinergics?","options":{"A":"Dopamine agonistic effect","B":"Nicotinic stimulation","C":"Endorphin release","D":"Stimulation of cannabinoid receptors","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Trihexyphenidyl is suspected to have some dopaminergic activities which produce stimulating effects. It has a higher abuse potential than other anticholinergic drugs. Smith JM. Abuse of the antiparkinson drugs: a review of the literature. Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 1980; 41: 351–354.152 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"All of the following measures help to reduce postural tremors induced by lithium therapy except","options":{"A":"Reducing caffeine intake","B":"Using propranolol","C":"Administering lithium at bed time","D":"Dose reduction","E":"Using procyclidine"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Lithium-induced tremor is frequently postural in nature and occurs at 8 to 12 Hz frequency. It is most notable in outstretched hands. If troublesome, the tremor can be reduced by giving lithium in divided doses or using a sustained release formulation wherein peaks and troughs in plasma level are better managed. A reduction in tremors can be noted if the patient’s anxiety is better managed and caffeine intake is reduced. β-blockers, such as propranolol, have been used to reduce lithium-induced tremor. If the tremors turn coarse, suspect lithium toxicity. Procyclidine can alleviate extrapyramidal symptoms but it has no effects on lithium-induced tremors. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1059."},{"question":"The half-life of donepezil in an elderly patient with dementia is around","options":{"A":"70 hours","B":"24 hours","C":"12 hours","D":"6 hours","E":"3 hours"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Donepezil is an anticholinesterase drug widely used in patients with a moderate degree of Alzheimer’s dementia. It is administered orally once daily. The half-life of donepezil is 70 hours in the elderly and steady-state levels are achieved within about 2 weeks. The half-life of rivastigmine, another antidementia drug, is 1 hour, but it dissociates slowly from cholinesterase enzyme, thus a single dose is therapeutically active for 10 hours. Rivastigmine is taken twice daily. Galantamine is an alkaloid (extracted from daffodils (Narcissus pseudonarcissus) and snow drops (Galanthus nivalis)); it has an elimination half-life of nearly 6 hours, and so is administered twice daily. A sustained release preparation is now available. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1034."},{"question":"A patient taking disulfi ram to support abstinence from alcohol decides to yield to his temptation and starts drinking but only a day after stopping disulfi ram. Which one of the following is correct in this scenario?","options":{"A":"Disulfi ram irreversibly damages alcohol dehydrogenase.","B":"Disulfi ram has a half-life of around 100 hours.","C":"Severity of the interaction does not depend on the dose of either agent.","D":"Disulfi ram competitively inhibits aldehyde dehydrogenase.","E":"None of the above."},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Alcohol (ethanol) is metabolized via an oxidation reaction catalysed by alcohol dehydrogenase. This results in formation of acetaldehyde, which is further broken down to acetyl-coenzyme A by aldehyde dehydrogenase. Disulfi ram is a non-competitive, irreversible aldehyde dehydrogenase inhibitor. So when alcohol is taken together with disulfi ram this leads to accumulation of acetaldehyde. A high level of acetaldehyde is associated with nausea, throbbing headache, vomiting, hypertension, fl ushing, sweating, thirst, dyspnoea, tachycardia, chest pain, vertigo, and blurred vision. The accumulation of acetaldehyde occurs almost immediately after the ingestion of alcohol in those who take disulfi ram; the reaction can last from 30 minutes to 2 hours. The initiation of disulfi ram should not take place unless the patient has abstained from alcohol for at least 12 hours. Its half-life is estimated to be 60 to 120 hours. The effect of disulfi ram treatment can last as long as 1 or 2 weeks after the last dose of disulfi ram. Most fatal reactions occur in persons who are taking more than 500 mg a day of disulfi ram and who consume more than 90 g of alcohol. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1039. Deitrich RA and Erwin VG. Mechanism of the inhibition of aldehyde dehydrogenase in vivo by disulfi ram and diethyldithiocarbamate. Molecular Pharmacology 1971; 7: 301–307.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 153"},{"question":"Smoking can reduce extrapyramidal side-effects caused by antipsychotics through","options":{"A":"Induction of hepatic metabolism of antipsychotics","B":"Increased renal elimination of antipsychotics","C":"Intestinal ischaemia reducing drug absorption","D":"Effect of nicotine on skeletal muscles","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Cigarette smoking occurs at a very high rate in patients with schizophrenia. Many reasons have been proposed as to why such high rates of smoking are seen in schizophrenia patients. One suggestion is that patients smoke as a form of self-medication with nicotine, which may help to regulate a dysfunctional mesolimbic dopamine system. Nicotine can increase dopamine release in the prefrontal cortex and reduce negative symptoms to some extent. Nicotine could enhance cognitive performance for certain tasks. Antipsychotic medications could block the dopamine reward pathway, necessitating an increase in nicotine concentrations needed to produce reward effects from smoking. Smoking may decrease the plasma levels of typical antipsychotic drugs via induction of the CYP450 enzymes system, providing some relief from extrapyramidal side-effects, but most patients who smoke start smoking even before onset of the illness. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1050. Kelly C and McCreadie R. Cigarette smoking and schizophrenia. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2000; 6: 327–331."},{"question":"Acamprosate is used in the management of alcohol dependence. Which of the following is correct?","options":{"A":"Acamprosate must be started preferably 2 weeks before the deadline to stop drinking.","B":"Acamprosate is started only after abstinence is achieved.","C":"Acamprosate has no demonstrable effect on craving.","D":"Consuming alcohol when taking acamprosate will produce fatal toxicity.","E":"Acamprosate increases levels of disulfi ram to a toxic range."},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Acamprosate is a structural analogue of GABA and taurine. Its mechanism of action is thought to be antagonism of glutamatergic N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptors. It should only be started after the individual has been successfully weaned off alcohol; this is not because of alcohol–acamprosate interaction but the effi cacy of acamprosate is demonstrated only in individuals who have been successfully detoxifi ed from alcohol. The concomitant intake of alcohol and acamprosate does not affect the pharmacokinetics of either alcohol or acamprosate, but if the patient relapses more than once while on acamprosate the treatment must be reconsidered. Administration of disulfi ram does not affect the pharmacokinetics of acamprosate; though this is practiced at certain centres, no strong evidence exists to support the combination. Bupropion, used to aid abstinence from smoking, is started 2 weeks before a target date is set to quit smoking. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1039."},{"question":"The most common reason for using dantrolene sodium in psychiatric patients is","options":{"A":"Serotonin syndrome","B":"Catatonia","C":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","D":"Dystonia","E":"Chorea"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Dantrolene sodium is used to treat rigidity and hyperthermia in patients with neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS). Dantrolene binds to a calcium channel called ryanodine receptor in skeletal muscle, leading to a fall in intracellular calcium concentration and reduced contraction. It is usually administered via the intravenous route; it reduces muscle spasm in most patients with neuroleptic malignant syndrome. Dantrolene is not a stand-alone treatment for NMS; it must be accompanied by resuscitation, fl uid replacement, and cardiac and respiratory support. Rigidity is relieved usually within minutes to hours of administration. Dantrolene can also be used in other cases of life-threatening muscle rigidity, for example catatonia and serotonin syndrome. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1037."},{"question":"Which of the following is correctly paired?","options":{"A":"Pimozide: phenothiazine","B":"Chlorpromazine: diphenyl butyl piperidine","C":"Trifl uperazine: aliphatic phenothiazine","D":"Thioridazine: dibenzoxapine","E":"Haloperidol: butyrophenone"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Haloperidol is chemically a butyrophenone. Fluphenazine, perphenazine, and trifl uperazine are piperazine phenothiazines. Chlorpromazine is an aliphatic phenothiazine while thioridazine is a piperidine phenothiazine. Thiothixene is a thioxanthene antipsychotic; pimozide is a diphenyl butyl piperidine. Loxapine is a dibenzoxapine. Many of these typical antipsychotics are rarely used in current practice. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1047.154 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"The most prominent mechanism of action of lamotrigine is","options":{"A":"Calcium channel blockade","B":"Voltage-sensitive sodium channel blockade","C":"Glutamate antagonism","D":"Serotonin reuptake inhibition","E":"GABA potentiation"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Lamotrigine is an anticonvulsant increasingly being used to prevent recurrent depressive episodes in bipolar disorder. Lamotrigine is thought to act via blockade of voltage-sensitive sodium channels, with secondary effect on calcium transport. Lamotrigine has weak effects on the serotonin system. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1054."},{"question":"The ECG changes produced by long-term lithium therapy mimic which one of the following electrolyte disturbances?","options":{"A":"Hyperkalaemia","B":"Hypokalaemia","C":"Hypocalcaemia","D":"Hypercalcaemia","E":"Hyperuricaemia"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Lithium produces hypokalaemia-like changes on the electrocardiogram (ECG). This is related to displacement of intracellular potassium by the lithium ion. T-wave fl attening or inversion is the commonest ECG change reported. These changes commonly disappear after stopping lithium. Lithium depresses the sinoatrial node; this can lead to sinus dysrhythmia, heart block, and syncope. Hence lithium is contraindicated in persons with sick sinus syndrome. Cardiac effects of lithium are more pronounced in those who have pre-existing cardiac problems, on diuretic treatment, and in those with renal impairment. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1059."},{"question":"A 34-year-old lady with bipolar disorder responds well to lamotrigine. She develops a minor maculopapular rash 6 months after the onset of treatment. The most appropriate line of action is","options":{"A":"Discontinue lamotrigine","B":"Persevere with lamotrigine as the rash is only minor","C":"This is very common and needs antihistaminic prescription","D":"Refer to dermatology but continue lamotrigine","E":"Reassure the patient and reduce the dose"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Lamotrigine is associated with rash, which is benign in about 8% of patients started on lamotrigine within the fi rst 4 months of treatment. In a small but signifi cant proportion of patients (nearly 0.1%) this may be an early manifestation of Stevens–Johnson syndrome or toxic epidermal necrolysis. So lamotrigine must be discontinued whenever a rash is reported during treatment. Unfortunately, this discontinuation is not always suffi cient to prevent the life threatening-hypersensitivity reaction, Steven–Johnson syndrome. The chances of developing a rash increases if lamotrigine is started at a higher than recommended dose or titrated at a faster than recommended speed. Coadministration of valproate can also increase the incidence of rash. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1054."},{"question":"ECT is widely used to treat resistant and psychotic depression. Which of the following statements is correct with respect to the clinical use of ECT?","options":{"A":"Seizure threshold varies widely among different individuals.","B":"Seizure threshold is fi xed for each individual once the treatment is started.","C":"No correlation exist between electrical dose and amnesia.","D":"I ncidence of cognitive disturbance is irrespective of the weekly frequency of administration.","E":"None of the above."},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The electrical stimulus delivered via ECT must be strong enough to reach the seizure threshold of the patient. Each individual has a different seizure threshold with nearly 40-fold variability among patients. During the course of ECT treatment itself, the seizure threshold could increase in the range of 25 to 200%. Older men generally have a higher threshold than the young. Amnesia related to ECT is proportional to the degree to which the administered electricity dose is high in relation to patients’ seizure thresholds. Incidence of cognitive disturbance is higher when a patient receives thrice-weekly ECT compared to twice-weekly treatments. UK ECT Review Group. Effi cacy and safety of electroconvulsive therapy in depressive disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet 2003; 361: 799–808."},{"question":"Which one of the following antidepressants resembles amphetamine in chemical structure?","options":{"A":"Buspirone","B":"Bupropion","C":"Imipramine","D":"Nortriptyline","E":"Duloxetine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Bupropion resembles amphetamine in its structure—it is a monocyclic aminoketone. Bupropion is a norepinephrine and dopamine reuptake inhibitor. Its side-effects profi le is different from that of SSRIs in that it causes very low incidence of sexual dysfunction or sedation and produces some weight loss. It does not cause signifi cant discontinuation reactions. It is currently licensed to help people quit smoking, but is not licensed as an antidepressant in the UK. Bupropion is contraindicated in patients with a history of eating disorder; it can cause signifi cant changes in appetite. Bupropion has a high propensity to cause seizures. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan and Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2007, p. 1024.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 155"},{"question":"Which of the following antidepressants is used by urologists for patients with incontinence?","options":{"A":"Citalopram","B":"Nortriptyline","C":"Paroxetine","D":"Duloxetine","E":"Venlafaxine"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"In the UK, duloxetine is marketed to treat stress urinary incontinence (SUI) in women under the name Yentreve® (Eli Lilly and Company). The female urethra has a rhabdosphincter of circularly arranged striated muscles. Generally, relaxation of this sphincter allows micturition. The sphincter is innervated by neurones from the sacral spinal cord (S2–S4). Duloxetine blocks the reuptake of serotonin and norepinephrine at this site to stimulate contraction of the rhabdosphincter, leading to an increase in the tone of the urethral sphincter. The increased muscle tone inhibits involuntary urine loss. To treat stress incontinence, a dose of 40 mg twice daily (80 mg/day) is recommended. In depression a dose of 60 mg/day given once daily is often used. Duloxetine can also help neuropathic pain, where a higher dose of up to 120 mg has been used. Thor KB. Serotonin and norepinephrine involvement in efferent pathways to the urethral rhabdosphincter: implications for treating stress urinary incontinence. Urology 2003; 62: 3–9."},{"question":"Which one of the following can increase plasma levels of lamotrigine?","options":{"A":"Lorazepam","B":"Chlorpromazine","C":"Valproate","D":"Carbamazepine","E":"Zopiclone"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Lamotrigine is mainly metabolized via glucuronidation and does not have much effect on other prescribed medications, but valproate has been observed to double the plasma levels of lamotrigine. The elimination half-life of lamotrigine in healthy young adults is approximately 25 to 30 hours. In patients taking valproate this is prolonged to 60 hours. As a result, when lamotrigine is initiated for patients who are taking valproate, the starting dose should be approximately 50% of the normal starting dose of lamotrigine. Some suggest that if valproate is started for a patient who is already on lamotrigine, one must consider obtaining a baseline lamotrigine plasma concentration. The lamotrigine dose may have to be reduced during the valproate dose titration. As a result of this interaction, the incidence of lamotrigine-induced rash seems to be more common in those taking the combination. Phenytoin, carbamazepine, and oral contraceptives may reduce the half-life of lamotrigine. Anderson GD, Yau MK, Gidal BE et al. Bidirectional interaction of valproate and lamotrigine in healthy subjects. Clinical Pharmacology and Theraputics 1996; 60: 145–156."},{"question":"One of your regular out-patients with recurrent depression was recently started on a medication but comes back with aggravated psoriatic skin lesions. The most probable offending agent is","options":{"A":"Lithium","B":"Valproate","C":"Olanzapine","D":"Zopiclone","E":"Chlorpromazine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Lithium can aggravate psoriasis. The induction of psoriasis without pre-existing disease is less common than exacerbation of existing disease. Not all patients with pre-existing psoriasis have a fl are when starting lithium and psoriasis is not considered to be a contraindication to taking lithium for mania or depression. Similarly, other drugs such as β-blockers, antimalarials, and indometacin can aggravate psoriasis. Psoriasis that has fl ared with lithium appears to be more resistant to standard treatment modalities. Some preliminary evidence suggests that supplemental inositol or omega-3-fatty acids may improve symptoms in patients with psoriasis during lithium treatment. Histological studies on the skin lesions induced or aggravated by lithium are equivocal; some support the lesions to be consistent with psoriasis, although others have claimed the features as non-specifi c and refer to as psoriasiform dermatitis. Fry L and Baker BS. Triggering psoriasis: the role of infections and medications. Clinics in Dermatology 2007; 25: 606–615.156 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"A 34-year-old man taking lithium twice daily experiences side-effects. Your consultant has advised him to take it once daily to reduce the side-effect. Which one of the following side-effects may respond to this intervention?","options":{"A":"Fine tremors","B":"Lethargy","C":"Polyuria","D":"Hypothyroidism","E":"Gastrointestinal distress"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Ployuria, one of the most common side-effects of lithium, is related to tubular concentrating defect that is resistant to vasopressin. This results in nephrogenic diabetes insipidus. Vasopressin receptor expression is reduced by lithium, leading to a failure of facilitation of water movement. It is thought that taking lithium in a single dose prevents, or at least limits, renal tubular impairment. The most likely reason for the reduction of thirst and polyuria is the less frequent stimulation of the thirst centre by the lithium salts in once-a-day doses. However, some studies have shown that the benefi cial effect of single dosage is seen only in those who received multiple doses for a short time. It is possible that long-term, multiple-dose administration results in irreversible changes in tubular mechanisms. Patient adherence can be improved by a single-dosing schedule of lithium; however, once-a-day schedules have not been shown to be conclusively superior with respect to glomerular damage or renal failure. Ljubicic D, Letica-Crepulja M, Vitezic D et al. Lithium treatments: single and multiple daily dosing. Canadian Journal of Psychiatry 2008; 53: 323–331."},{"question":"An intoxicated patient needs prescription for alcohol withdrawal. He is known to have cirrhosis with ascites. The benzodiazepine of choice is","options":{"A":"Diazepam","B":"Chlordiazepoxide","C":"Alprazolam","D":"Midazolam","E":"Oxazepam"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"On pharmacokinetic grounds, oxazepam may be preferable to chlordiazepoxide in cirrhotic patients since the elimination of oxazepam is not greatly altered in cirrhosis. In general, longer-acting benzodiazepines, such as chlordiazepoxide or diazepam, are preferred as they produce a smoother withdrawal course with less breakthrough or rebound symptoms, but they may lead to excess sedation for patients with hepatic dysfunction/cirrhosis. Shorter-acting benzodiazepines, such as oxazepam, may result in greater discomfort and more discharges against medical advice, because alcohol withdrawal symptoms tend to recur when the plasma drug levels drop. Shorter-acting agents, such as lorazepam or oxazepam, require more frequent dosing. They may be more useful for symptom-triggered regimens than fi xed-dose regimens of alcohol detoxifi cation. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 9th edn. Informa Healthcare, 2007, p. 237."},{"question":"Regular, long-term prescription of anticholinergics increases the risk of","options":{"A":"Akathisia","B":"Dytonia","C":"Parkinsonism","D":"Tardive dyskinesia","E":"Torticollis"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Anticholinergic drugs may exacerbate some symptoms of tardive dyskinesia (TD). Traditionally, long-term anticholinergic prescriptions are thought to promote the onset of TD, though the evidence in support of this notion is minimal. Tardive dyskinesia is a troublesome side- effect of antipsychotics. It is more common in older patients and those with neurological diseases. The risk of tardive dyskinesia is estimated as 3–5% per year of exposure (at least for the fi rst 5 years) with conventional antipsychotics. The appearance of symptoms usually takes more than 3 months, the risk increasing proportionally with duration of treatment. In elderly patients this increases to be as high as 25% within the fi rst year of exposure to typical antipsychotics. Women, children, and patients with primary mood disorders or learning disabilities are also at higher risk. Some studies report an increased risk associated with diabetes and comorbid substance use. Tasman A, Maj M et al., eds. Psychiatry, 3rd edn. John Wiley and Sons, 2008, p. 1783."},{"question":"Select one drug associated with gastrointestinal bleeding","options":{"A":"Benzodiazepines","B":"SSRIs","C":"MAOIs","D":"Methadone","E":"Bupropion"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Serotonin is released from platelets in response to vascular injury. It promotes vasoconstriction and platelet aggregation. Platelets do not possess the synthetic machinery to produce serotonin and so depend on uptake via 5-HT transporters on their membrane. SSRIs inhibit the serotonin transporter, leading to a hyposerotonergic state in platelets. This reduces the ability to form clots, with subsequent increase in the risk of bleeding. Thus, SSRIs cause a functional impairment of platelet aggregation (thrombasthenia), but not a reduction in platelet number. This can cause easy bruising or prolonged bleeding in those with gastric ulcers or bleeding diathesis. Some authors recommend gastroprotection when SSRIs are coadministered with NSAIDs. Paton C and Ferrier IN. SSRIs and gastrointestinal bleeding. BMJ 2005; 331: 529–530.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 157"},{"question":"Which of the following is a partial agonist at nicotinic acetylcholine receptors that can be used to promote smoking cessation?","options":{"A":"Varenicline","B":"Bupropion","C":"Ticarcilline","D":"Dosulepin","E":"Gallantamine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Varenicline is a partial agonist at the αβ unit of the nicotinic acetylcholine receptor. It 4 2 is shown to assist smoking cessation by relieving nicotine withdrawal symptoms and reducing the rewarding properties of nicotine. It is advised to choose a quitting date and start taking the tablets 1 week before the date. Generally, varenicline is started at 0.5 mg daily, increasing to"},{"question":"A 48-year-old man taking multiple drugs for hypertension, diabetes, and bipolar disorder presents with disabling impotence. Which of the following drugs that he might be using is not associated with sexual dysfunction?","options":{"A":"Atenolol","B":"Fluphenazine","C":"Glibenclamide","D":"Thiazide diuretics","E":"α1-blocker"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"All of the listed drugs except α-blockers are associated with erectile dysfunction. 1 Parasympathetic activity during arousal triggers the release of nitric oxide, which increases the levels of the intracellular cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP). Increases in cGMP cause penile vascular and trabecular smooth muscle relaxation, leading to increase in blood fl ow. The rapid fi lling of the cavernosal spaces compresses venules leading to reduction in venous outfl ow. This process effectively raises intracavernosal pressure, resulting in erection. α adrenergic 1 blockers can enhance erectile function by reducing the sympathetic tone and relaxing trabecular smooth muscle cells. Nearly 25% of cases of erectile dysfunction are related to medication side-effects. Many prescribed drugs, including β-blockers, H antagonists, diuretics, antiepileptics, 2 antidepressants, and antiparkinsonian medications, can cause erectile dysfunction. In addition, street drugs such as cannabis, cocaine, alcohol, ecstasy, and opiates can also lead to impotence. Tasman A, Maj M et al., eds. Psychiatry, 3rd edn. John Wiley and Sons, 2008, p. 1588."},{"question":"A 40-year-old man with chronic dysthymia also suffers from impotence unrelated to his depression. His GP prescribes him a medication to be used prior to the sexual act, as and when required. Which of the following describes the most likely mechanism of action of the prescribed drug?","options":{"A":"Prostaglandin precursor","B":"Selective phosphodiesterase type 5 inhibition","C":"Selective serotonin uptake inhibition","D":"Dopamine agonist","E":"α adrenoceptor blockade"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The vasodilatation required to bring on erection is mediated by nitric oxide (NO). Nitric oxide enables vascular smooth muscle relaxation via production of a second messenger, called cGMP. Men suffering from erectile dysfunction (ED) may have successful erection if the availability of cGMP is prolonged or increased. This can be achieved by modulating an enzyme called phosphodiesterase (PDE-5). Normally PDE-5 terminates the action of cGMP by converting it into inactive form (GMP). By inhibiting PDE-5, sildenafi l lengthens the life of cGMP and helps to achieve erection. There are nine different types of PDE found in different tissues of the body; for example coronary tissues have the PDE-3 type receptors; PDE-5 receptors are found in platelets and various muscle tissues; and PDE-6 receptors are found in the retina. Sildenafi l has some propensity to act on PDE-6, apart from its primary action on PDE-5; this explains defects in colour vision experienced by some patients taking sildenafi l. As sildenafi l does not produce new cGMP directly, it cannot act as an aphrodisiac. Hence it cannot help patients with reduced arousal due to other causes such as depression. Francis SH and Corbin JD. Sildenafi l: effi cacy, safety, tolerability and mechanism of action in treating erectile dysfunction. Expert Opinion on Drug Metabolism and Toxicology 2005; 1: 283–293.158 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following opioids produces metabolites with clinically useful analgesic activity?","options":{"A":"Naloxone","B":"Nomifensine","C":"Propoxyphene","D":"Codeine","E":"Naltrexone"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Naloxone is an opioid antagonist and has no analgesic activities. Naltrexone is a longer- acting opioid antagonist with no clinically useful analgesic actions. Nomifensine is not an opioid; it is a cyclic antidepressant with norepinephrine and dopamine reuptake inhibition. It was withdrawn from the clinical market due to hepatotoxicity and renal damage, in addition to fears regarding abuse potential. Propoxyphene has mild to moderate analgesic properties but its metabolite, norpropoxyphene, is devoid of clinically useful analgesia. Codeine, on the other hand, is a strong analgesic and breaks down to morphine which has potent analgesic activity. Codeine is ineffective as an analgesic at usual doses in 7 to 10% of the white population with low activity CYP2D6 alleles. It is reported that in those with ultrarapid CYP2D6 metabolism, codeine intake may result in an increase in morphine production, occasionally resulting in opioid intoxication. Yue QY, Alm C, Svensson JO, and Sawe J. Quantifi cation of the O- and N-demethylated and the glucuronidated metabolites of codeine relative to the debrisoquine metabolic ratio in urine in ultrarapid, rapid, and poor debrisoquine hydroxylators. Therapeutic Drug Monitoring 1997; 19: 539–542."},{"question":"The mechanism of action of opioids in producing an analgesic effect is","options":{"A":"Blockade of sodium channels on the neuronal membrane (membrane stabilization)","B":"Increased production of cAMP in a neurone","C":"Reduction in intracellular calcium in a neurone","D":"Stimulation of Gs–protein-coupled receptors in the neurone","E":"Direct action on nuclear transcription factors"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"There are three important types of opioid receptors; most analgesic effects are associated with µ receptors. The δ and κ receptors also contribute to the analgesic effect to some extent. Morphine and codeine mainly act via µ receptors to produce clinical analgesia. Opioids are coupled to Gi proteins that decrease cAMP. When opioids bind to µ receptors, hyperpolarization of the nociceptive neurone (sensory neurone for pain) takes place via opening of K+ channels and inhibition of the Ca2+ channels. This reduces neuronal activity and reduces the transmission of pain signals via ascending pathways to the brain. Stein C, Schäfer M, and Machelska H. Attacking pain at its source: new perspectives on opioids. Nature Medicine 2003; 9: 1003–1008."},{"question":"Methylxanthines produce stimulation of the CNS via their action on which of the following receptors?","options":{"A":"NMDA receptors","B":"Adenosine receptors","C":"Nicotinic receptors","D":"GABA receptors","E":"Cholinergic muscarinic receptors"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Methylxanthines include caffeine and theophylline. They have CNS stimulatory properties. At therapeutic doses, these drugs block adenosine receptors; at higher concentrations inhibition of the phosphodiesterase enzyme takes place. Adenosine is released from neurones and glia. It acts via G-protein-coupled receptors (A, A , A , and A). A receptors have inhibitory role 1 2A 2B 3 1 whileA receptors have stimulatory properties.A receptor antagonism may enhance cognition 2 1 and facilitate arousal. At higher doses where inhibition of phosphodiesterase occurs, intracellular levels of cAMP increase. Abbracchio MP and Cattabeni F. Brain adenosine receptors as targets for therapeutic intervention in neurodegenerative diseases. Annals of the New York Academy of Science 1999; 890: 79–92."},{"question":"Which of the following medications used for Parkinson’s disease is correctly paired with its side-effect?","options":{"A":"Levodopa–hypoglycaemia","B":"Bromocriptine–hyperprolactinaemia","C":"Amantadine–livedo reticularis","D":"Tolcapone–gouty arthritis","E":"Bromocriptine–aplastic anaemia"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Livedo reticularis refers to a characteristic purple mottling of the skin see in patients taking amantadine. It is usually seen as a lacy, net-like pattern of vascular change on the legs. It is also associated with vasculitis such as lupus. Mostly, the livedo reticularis disappears when the drug is discontinued, usually within several weeks. The appearance of livedo does not always warrant the cessation of the drug. The common side-effects of levodopa include insomnia, postural hypotension, gastrointestinal disturbances, tremors, mood changes, and fatigue. Bromocriptine can cause postural hypotension, nausea, oedema, confusion, dry mouth, and depression. Tolcapone is a COMT inhibitor and can cause abdominal pain, back pain, constipation, nausea, diarrhoea, and liver failure. Sladden MJ, Nicolaou N, Johnston GA et al. Livedo reticularis induced by amantadine. British Journal of Dermatology 2003; 149: 656–658.PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 159"},{"question":"Which of the following agents acts through glial/ neuronal GABA reuptake inhibition?","options":{"A":"Zopiclone","B":"Vigabatrin","C":"Topiramate","D":"Tiagabine","E":"Gabapentin"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Tiagabine is an add-on antiepileptic drug developed by modifying a GABA uptake inhibitor called nipecotic acid. Tiagabine is a potent inhibitor of GABA uptake into both neurones and glial cells. It acts via selective inhibition of the GABA transporter, GAT-1. Through this mechanism, tiagabine enhances GABA receptor-mediated tonic inhibition. Vigabatrin is a A selective and irreversible GABA-transaminase inhibitor. Topiramate produces its antiepileptic effect through several mechanisms such as modifi cation of Na+-dependent and/or Ca2+- dependent action potentials, enhancement of GABA-mediated Cl– fl uxes into neurones, and inhibition of kainate-mediated conductance at AMPA glutamate receptors. Gabapentin is a structural analogue of GABA and though originally designed as a GABA-mimetic, its mechanism of action is still unknown. Perucca E. Clinical pharmacology and therapeutic use of the new antiepileptic drugs. Fundamental and Clinical Pharmacology 2001; 15: 405–417."},{"question":"Which of the following neuropharmacological agents is described as a melatonergic antidepressant?","options":{"A":"Agomelatine","B":"L-tryptophan","C":"Melatonin","D":"Modafi nil","E":"Ropinirole"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Melatonin has not been demonstrated to have clinically signifi cant antidepressant properties. Ropinirole is a dopamine agonist; it acts via the stimulation of postsynaptic dopamine D-type receptors within the basal ganglia. Agomelatine is a novel agent promoted as a 2 melatonergic antidepressant; its main antidepressant effect is mediated via 5-HT antagonism, 2C which may modulate noradrenergic and dopaminergic neurotransmission. L-tryptophan is a serotonin precursor and is not considered as melatonergic drug. Modafi nil is not used as an antidepressant; it acts via an infl uence on dopamine-dependent adrenergic signalling, though the exact mechanism is still unclear. Palaniyappan L and McAllister-Williams RH. Antidepressants: will new mechanisms of action improve poor outcomes? British Journal of Hospital Medicine (Lond) 2008; 69: 88–90."},{"question":"Which of the following medications can be used to treat narcolepsy and associated sleep disorders?","options":{"A":"Buprenorphine","B":"Fluoxetine","C":"Imipramine","D":"Modafi nil","E":"Naloxone"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Buprenorphine and naloxone act via opioid receptors; they are not indicated in sleep disorders such as narcolepsy. Antidepressants, including fl uoxetine and tricyclics such as imipramine, can help cataplexy (sudden loss of muscle tone) in narcolepsy. Modafi nil is a drug with stimulant properties and it is used to promote wakefulness in narcolepsy and allied disorders. Dauvilliers Y, Arnulf I, and Mignot E. Narcolepsy with cataplexy. Lancet 2007; 369: 499–511."},{"question":"Which of the following drugs has some evidence for the treatment of resistant depression as an augmenting agent to SSRIs?","options":{"A":"Atenolol","B":"Labetolol","C":"Pentazocine","D":"Pindolol","E":"Tramadol"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Pindolol acts as a partial agonist at 5-HT receptors. Several controlled studies in the 1A past have shown that the addition of pindolol to SSRI therapy rapidly potentiates the effects of these antidepressants. However, despite the rapidity of improvement with the combination, most studies found no overall advantage at the end of the study period. Systematic review of randomized controlled trials does not support the use of pindolol and β-blockers are not licensed for the treatment of depression. Pentazocine is a partial agonist at kappa opiate receptors; it has some psychotomimetic properties but is not used as an antidepressant. In fact, it may induce depression. Tramadol is an opioid analgesic with no antidepressant effects. Stimpson N, Agrawal N, and Lewis G. Randomized controlled trials investigating pharmacological and psychological interventions for treatment-refractory depression. Systematic review. British Journal of Psychiatry 2002; 181: 284–294.160 PHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"The half-life of atomoxetine in most individuals is","options":{"A":"2 weeks","B":"24 hours","C":"36 hours","D":"5 days","E":"5 hours"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The mean elimination half-life of atomoxetine after oral administration is 5.2 hours. In poor metabolizers (CYP2D6 polymorphism) the mean elimination half-life is more than 20 hours, due to reduced clearance. Nearly 80% of atomoxetine is excreted in the urine. Atomoxetine does not affect the cytochrome P450 2D6 enzyme system. The effects of atomoxetine last longer than would be expected from its half-life; hence, once-daily administration is effective. Barton, J. Atomoxetine: a new pharmacotherapeutic approach in the management of attention defi cit/hyperactivity disorder. Archives of Diseases in Childhood 2005; 90 (Suppl. I): i26–i29."},{"question":"Which of the following is considered to be the safest of all MAO-A inhibitors when used in combination with other antidepressants to treat depression?","options":{"A":"Isocarboxazid","B":"Isoniazid","C":"Phenelzine","D":"Selegiline","E":"Tranylcypromine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Antidepressant combinations involving MAOIs require close monitoring due to the risk of serotonergic and hypertensive side-effects. Phenelzine is supposed to be the safest MAO-A inhibitor in combination therapy for depression. It is a derivative of hydrazine similar to isonaizid, but the latter is mainly used as an antituberculosis drug and has only a weak antidepressant action. Selegeline is an MAO-B inhibitor. Palaniyappan L, Insole L, and Ferrier IN. Combining antidepressants: a review of evidence. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 2009; 15: 90–99."}]');export{e as default};
